<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sylvia Beach Papers, 1872-1999</title>
                <author>Sylvia Beach</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Princeton University, Department of Special Collections</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Draft of Sylvia Beach prose with hand-written edits.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>It was in the summer of 1920, a few months after Shakespeare and Company was opened that my first meeting with <persName key="Pers1">Joyce</persName> took place.</p>
            <p>One sultry Sunday afternoon <persName key="Pers2">Adrienne</persName> was going to a party at <persName key="Pers3">André Spire's</persName>. I wasn't invited, but <persName key="Pers2">Adrienne</persName> insisted on my going with her, assuring me that <persName key="Pers4">Monsieur</persName> and <persName key="Pers5">Madame Spire</persName> would be delighted. I hung back but she had her way and I went. I liked <persName key="Pers3">André Spire's</persName> poetry, but didn't know him personally.</p>
            <p>The Spires were living at that time in a little house <del method="pen" rend="overwritten">at</del><add place="overwrite">in</add> Neuilly, right in the middle of the Bois de Boulogne. It was <del method="pen" rend="overwritten">surr</del><add place="overwrite">supp</add>ounded with green trees <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">and a lot of birds</del><add place="above" method="pen">swarming with singing</add><del rend="strikethrough">were singing in them</del> - what could be a lovelier place to spend a hot Sunday<del method="pen" rend="overwritten">?</del><add place="overwrite">?</add> The windows were all open, guests were assembling and <persName key="Pers3">André Spire</persName> stood at the top of the steps with <persName key="Pers5">Madame Spire</persName>, greeting everybody, even uninvited persons like me, with the greatest hospitality. <persName key="Pers3">Spire</persName> drew me aside and whispered in my ear: "the Irish writer <persName key="Pers6">James Joyce</persName> is here". <persName key="Pers6">James Joyce</persName>! When I realized what he was saying I was terrified. I wanted to run away. But <persName key="Pers3">Spire</persName> <del method="pen" rend="strikethough">was</del> point<del method="pen" rend="overwritten">ing out</del><add place="overwrite">ed To</add> <persName key="Pers7">Ezra Pound</persName> - it was <persName key="Pers7">Pound</persName> who brought the Joyces, he told me.</p>
            <p>
                <surface>
                    <zone xml:id="added_paper">Rectangular slice of paper the length of three lines of printed text.</zone>
                    <add place="#added_paper" method="pasted">There, indeed, was <persName key="Pers7">Ezra</persName>. <add place="above" method="pen">So I went into the house.</add> stretched over a chair, handsome in a blue shirt open at the neck, with his tawny beard and his velvet jacket, and surrounded by his friends bending to catch his mysterious mutterances.</add>
                </surface>
                I went over to greet <persName key="Pers8">Dorothy Pound</persName>. She was talking to someone whom she introduced as <persName key="Pers9">Mrs. Joyce</persName>. <persName key="Pers9">Mrs. Joyce</persName> was <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">rather</del><add place="above" method="pen">a rather</add> tall <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">with curly auburn hair and eyelashes that were curly too. She had an Irish humor and voice with delightful inflections, and the Irish warmth. </del> <add method="pen">round-shaped young woman, with curly reddish hair and eyelashes and a voice that with its Irish inflections was warmth was delightful.</add> <del method="pen" rend="overwritten">She </del><add place="overwrite">Her manner was <add place="above" method="pen">dignified and at the same time humorous.</add></add> She said <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">how glad</del> she was <add method="pen">glad</add> to find someone she could talk English with - she couldn't understand a word of <del method="pen" rend="overwritten"><gap reason="overwrite"/></del><add place="overwrite">the French conversation going on around her. </add> Now if it had been Italian, she knew that - they <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">had</del> lived<del><gap reason="illegible"/></del><add place="above">for years</add> in Trieste. They even spoke Italian in the family. <add place="above">(This Irish family, speaking Italian at home - why not? I thought.)</add>
            </p>
            <p>I would have liked to <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> more but <persName key="Pers3">Spire</persName> was <add place="above">loudly</add> inviting his guests <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">in a loud voice</del> to sit <del method="pen" rend="overwritten">ome </del><add place="overwrite">it</add> down at the long table and partake of the tempting cold lunch laid out on it. Soon we were passing out plates for big helpings of chicken, ham, <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del><add place="above">meat patties</add>, fish, salads <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">and mayonnaise</del><add place="above">etc. and breaking pieces of the long loaves as they passed from hand to hand.</add> <persName key="Pers3">Spire</persName> was filling glasses with red, white <add place="between">and</add> rosy wine. Everybody was busy munching and crunching, talking and laughing <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">as gay as could be</del> - everybody, but a man sitting about halfway down the table who <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del><del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">refusing the white wine his host was pressing on him, in vain.</del><add place="above">was discouraging every attempt of his host to fill up his glass with the white wine - finally</add><add place="below">turning his glass upside down...which ended the struggle.</add>
            <pb/> 
            was more like the language spoken on the stage than the <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">inarticulate kind</del><add place="above">modern Englishman's.</add> <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del><add place="below"><hi rend="underline">This might be attributed to the years spent</hi></add> teaching foreigners how to speak English. <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">it was mainly, on account of his ear for music</del><del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del><add place="above">Listening to him, one felt that he loved the English language.</add></p>
            <p> What did we talk about? Certainly not his books, but my bookshop. He asked me what I did: I told him about Shakespeare and Company. The name seemed to amuse him and <add place="above">a </add>charming smile came on his lips. Taking a small notebook out of his pocket, and holding it close to his eyes, as I noted <del method="pen" rend="overwrite"><gap reason="overwritten"/></del><add place="over">sadly</add>, he wrote in it my name, <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">and</del>, the name of the bookshop <gap reason="overwritten"/> and the address. He said "I'll go to see you". But suddenly a dog barked. <persName key="Pers1">Joyce</persName> turned pale. <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">and</del> he was actually trembling <del method="pen" rend="overwritten"><gap reason="overwritten"/></del><add place="over">ing</add> I looked out <add place="between">of</add> the window <del method="pen" rend="overwrite"><gap reason="overwritten"/></del><add place="over">ow</add> and saw <persName key="Pers3">Spire's</persName> little dog running after a ball that some of the guests were throwing him. "Is it fierce? Is it coming in?" <persName key="Pers1">Joyce</persName> asked me. I <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough">re</del>assured him that it wasn't fierce and it wasn't coming in. But he <del method="pen" rend="overwrite">still shuddered</del> every time he heard the barking. He explained his fear...<hi rend="underline">telling me that</hi>he had been bitten <add place="above">on the chin</add> by a dog at the age of five. <add place="between">that, pointing to his</add>goatee<del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del><add place="between">was</add> to cover the scar.</p>
            <p> The party was over, the guests saying goodbye and <persName key="Pers2">Adrienne</persName> was looking for me to take leave of <persName key="Pers3">André Spire</persName>. Again I grasped <persName key="Pers1">Joyce's</persName> delicate hand and heard him say he would go to see me. I went away feeling dizzy - feeling "transported into a country"...meeting <persName key="Pers1">James Joyce</persName>!</p>
            <p>He peered at <persName key="Pers10">Whitman</persName> and <persName key="Pers11">Poe</persName> and the two <persName key="Pers12">Blake</persName> drawings on the walls. He examined attentively the photos of <persName key="Pers13">Wilde</persName> in extravagant costumes framed with two of his letters, the gift of a friend named <persName key="Pers14">Byron Kuhn</persName>. Then he sat down by my table in the uncomfortable little armchair - the first of many times he sat in it.</p>
            <p>At first the conversation was about his arrival with his family in Paris. It was <persName key="Pers7">Pound</persName>, he said, who had persuaded him to come. Through <persName key="Pers7">Pound</persName>, he had met <persName key="Pers15">Madame Ludmila Savitzky</persName>, translator of "A Portrait of the Artist". She had kindly <del method="pen" rend="overwritten">let</del><add place="overwrite">allowed</add> the Joyces to occupy her flat in Passy while they looked for a permanent place to stay in - they <del method="pen" rend="overwritten">would only stay</del><add place="overwrite">would have to vacate it in</add> a fortnight. <del method="pen" rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="illegible"/></del> He said two problems were on his mind: the first: finding a roof to put over 
            the heads of four people: the second: feeding and clothing</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
